I'm the director of Utah's Office of Data
Privacy located in the Department of
Government Operations. I want to thank the
Herbert Institute of Public Policy, the
Department of Government Operations, and
the Utah Legislature for all helping to
host this event and also to UVU for
allowing us to use their facilities. I
also want to thank UVU. We had many
employees and students and interns help to
bring this event together for the last few
months and so we couldn't do this without
the work that they've been putting in. And
I want to thank all of you for coming to
Utah to participate in this event. We put
a lot of thought into how would we
actually host an event to cause change.
And we thought about just doing a virtual
event and we knew that it's going to take
a lot of passion and a lot of work to pull
off what we're going to be proposing
today. So it was important to see who can
we get to come in person that cares the
most about it to help us build what we are
going to be proposing. So I thank all of
you for coming. Those from states, we have
12 states represented. Those from
academia, those from executive branch
agencies, those from legislators. I think
we have more than a dozen companies
represented. We have concerned citizens.
We have private interest groups. We have
the national ACLU. So we have the start of
what I think is going to be a really great
consortium.
Now, the purpose of today is simple. We
invited you all to come here to one,
receive an education about a very complex
topic, is digital identity. The second
reason we've invited you is to help you
understand the problem and what we think
is a really big opportunity for America to
lead out. And the third and final reason
that we've invited you here today is to
actually invite you to join the SEDI
consortium, the state-endorsed digital
identity consortium, so that we can move
forward and work together on what we think
is a big opportunity for America. Now, I
am an optimist by nature and I'm very
optimistic about digital identity if we do
it right. And I believe that we can build
technology that reflects American values,
that protects freedoms and strengthens
families and builds trust in the digital
world. But I am also a realist about why
this effort is needed. I am very concerned
about some of what I see happening not
just in the United States, but what is
happening around the world. There are many
of you in this room that have expressed
those same concerns. That is why
Representative Cutler and Senator
Kullimore sponsored Senate Bill 260 this
last session, the first state-endorsed
digital identity bill in the and the
nation to begin addressing these concerns.
So I want to share with you some of our
concerns. I am concerned for my kids and
your kids who can engage online and video
games and social media and they do not
know and we do not know if the people they
are engaging with are actually who they
say they are. I am concerned for my and
your elderly parents and grandparents who
continue to be taken advantage of by
individuals pretending to be family
members in distress. I am concerned for
young men facing exploitation and
sextortion online. This is one of the
fastest growing crimes in America and in
Utah facing our young men. They are being
driven to despair and even suicide in a
world where anonymity and manipulation
coexist without protection. I am concerned
that fraud enabled by identity theft and
impersonation is now costing the United
States hundreds of billions of dollars a
year. I am concerned that algorithms based
on profiling and scoring are influencing
our behavior and quietly shaping the
concept of even freedom and free agency. I
am concerned that the free market is being
distorted, that those who control personal
data are facilitating monopolistic
behavior that maximizes exploitation of
individuals for profit instead of driving
a free market based off of competition and
best prices. I am concerned that nation
state attacks on future digital identity
systems will occur and we have to assume
digital identity will be compromised. I am
concerned that government-sponsored
digital identity systems both in the
United States and around the world have
been created that are capable of tracking,
surveilling, and controlling. I am
concerned that governments, corporations,
and technologists are rushing to create
digital identity systems that are
compulsory and are required and that these
are being created without the
comprehensive governance its frameworks
and protections needed to protect
individual rights. And I am most concerned
that in democracies around the world,
digital identity systems are being
designed and implemented in ways contrary
to the first principles of America's
founding. And that is that individuals
have individual inalienable rights that
they are endowed with that is innate to
them, including identity. Government does
not give identity. Government does not
create identity. And any identity system
built on the premise that government is
giving it to you means that they can also
take it away, which is in opposition to
this founding principle. So the truth is
there is no trust in the digital world
today. We don't know who or what is real.
We do not know. You do not control your
digital identity. Usernames, passwords,
even mobile driver's license can be taken
away. They can be compromised. There is
currently no national strategy for digital
identity and we know that there are many,
both foreign and abroad, who would love to
control your digital identity and
compromise it for their own gains. So the
dilemma before us is that if we do
nothing, we will be left with a system
created by others that do not share our
same values. But this is not the end of
the story. It is the reason that we are
here. All of us in this room are in a
position to influence. Some of you have
the power to create laws. Some of you have
the power to create and dictate public
policy. Some of you have the power to
create technology. Some of you have the
power to fund new businesses to create the
solutions that we need. Some of you have
the power to create governance frameworks.
And some of you have the power to create
standards. And some of you just have the
power to raise your concerns and create
trouble for the rest of us, which we need.
So you all have something to contribute
that is needed to create the solution
necessary to address our concerns and
create a better digital identity. So there
is a path a path forward by building
digital identity in a manner that
prioritizes rights and dignity. This is
what state endorsed digital identity is
all about. So I want you to imagine for a
minute a future. A future 10 years from
now after we've put in a lot of hard work.
We need to agree today and in future
summits what that work is going to be. But
a future where our fears about digital
identity theft, manipulation,
impersonation, exploitation, loss of
control have been replaced by trust and
authenticity. Where parents know their
children are safe online. Where our
elderly are protected from scams and
impersonation, where there is trust that
government is protecting your digital
identity and rights above all other
interests. That is the world we need all
of you to help create. So through the SEDI
consortium that we are proposing and
inviting you to join today, states will
work together to define an American model
for digital identity, one that protects
citizens, and instead of importing
surveillance and control-based standards
and technology from abroad, we will export
freedom by design, showing that privacy,
security, protection of rights and
protection of individual rights and
innovation can coexist. The benefits and
capabilities of SEDI will be profound. It
will provide the foundation for
individuals and businesses to derive value
and utility for the free market, to create
new and and innovative solutions. We know
there will be new solutions for proof of
identity. There will be new solutions for
replacements of usernames and passwords.
Imagine that if you don't have to worry
about your passwords being compromised.
There will be new solutions for consent
and management and agreements that
individuals control. There will be new
solutions for delegation, empowering
families and guardians and organizations
to act safely on behalf of the vulnerable
and those they serve. There will be
solutions for agentic AI where artificial
intelligence operates with your explicit
authorization and not in your place,
extending your agency rather than
replacing it. So many of you are probably
wondering, how would we ever get from the
current state to that future state? And we
do that the same way all great things are
done. And we have to do that together. We
have to create a plan. We have to agree on
our values. We have to create a structure.
We have to roll up our sleeves. And then,
as my teenagers and young kids like to
say, we have to grind. We're going to have
to get out there and actually do the work
to make it happen. And it is going to take
a long time. And under the SEDI consortium
is where we can take the fruits of all
these labors that we are about to do and
give them away to everyone else so that
they can follow us. We know not everybody
is going to be able to do this. We don't
have all 50 states here. Not everybody has
the funding, but but we are public
entities. We can create it and we can give
it to them for the good of everyone. So
the work we're going to do is going to
include comprehensive governance
frameworks, model legislation,
resolutions, executive orders, defining
SEDI requirements, technology and policy
controls, conformance programs, RFIs and
RFPs. We're going to have to do security
assessments. We're going to have to do
continuous engagement with civil rights
groups and watchdogs. We're going to have
to have absolute transparency and we're
going to have to have absolute
transparency and we're going to have to
have going to have to do much, much more
to move the digital identity market in
America to align with what are going to be
the SEDI standards.
So today you are here to learn about
digital identity and some of the
principles that will guide the creation of
state-endorsed digital identity. You will
understand the concerns and the
opportunities ahead of us and I hope you
will accept our invitation to join. But to
end, I'm going to teach you just one of
the founding principles and requirements
of state-endorsed digital identity. This
is the very first one that we identified
when Senate Bill 260 was written. And this
is probably the most foundational and
fundamental difference compared to what
you see happening in the rest of the
world. Identity belongs to the person, not
to the government. The government's role
is not to create or control identity, but
to endorse and protect it as a matter of
public trust. SEDI recognizes it is the
role of the state to act as a trusted
endorser, verifying an individual's
digital identity and then issuing an
endorsed credential mathematically bound
to a digital identifier that individuals
alone control. The state does not create
the individual identifier cannot revoke
it. The state simply endorses that the
person is who they say they are and then
provides a credential that empowers the
individual to say to the world that I am
me and the world will accept it because it
has been endorsed and backed by the state.
The state will have no control or ability
to surveil or to track the usage and the
state cannot take away the underlying
digital identifier. The state has no role
to take away anybody's digital identity.
So with that said, we have a very busy day
ahead of us. This is mostly about
introductory education. This is going to
be a very fast-paced style to get you
information. We'll have a couple breakouts
throughout the day where you can ask
questions and you can participate and
learn what it means to help define policy
and technical controls. We're going to end
at the end of the with an hour-long
discussion of how can we actually move
forward together as states. This morning,
the run of the show is we're going to have
Ryan Hurst speak to us and educate you on
what is digital identity. We will then
have Cindy George speaking to us about her
family's experience with sextortion and
impersonation and the impact it has had on
them through their son's suicide. We'll
then have a legislative panel of Senator
Kullimore, Representative Cutler,
Representative Chevrier, and
Representative Shepherd to discuss with
you the importance of this work, why they
are supporting it, and why you should be a
part of the consortium. We'll then hear
from Daniel Hardman who will teach us
about the current lay of the digital
identity market. Phil Windley will explain
why Utah is the first state to formally
take the decentralized or first-person
identity approach. And Joe Jackson will
teach you why we are moving forward with
backward compatibility to help the entire
market move forward. So with that, Ryan,
I'll invite you to come up. Thank you.